abuse of power
Excuse me, I'm thirsty.
The usual. Not too much ice.
- Hi, Enrico. - Hi.
Why don't you invite me to dinner?
I'm waiting for Rosenthal and
am busy later.
But Rosenthal is over there,
at the usual place.
You've never a whole evening
free for me, haven't you?
Be careful, that guy will
fleece you.
There's no danger, I'll settle
up with him tonight. Bye.
Have a seat.
I've calculated a month interest.
Check the money.
Won't you renew it? - No, I withdraw.
- What's the rush?
Do you have it?
- Yes, sure.
I repeat, there was no rush
at all.
You know, I'll be gone for
a while, so I prefer...
Mr Gagliardi, I only lend money
to people I trust,...
...and I have every confidence
in you.
Anyway, I wish you a safe journey.
Thanks.
Good evening.
You just had to meet that
bloodsucker right now?
Get in, we shouldn't be seen
together.
What about the papers? Have you
brought them? Where are they?
In safe hands, as it's not the
kind of stuff to carry around.
But, beware, those ones want the
money first. Do you have it all?
Where are we going? - Go all the way
to the gardens, then I'll tell you.
Where do we have to go?
- There, first door on the right.
Rosaria!
Ugly bitch!
They finished him off with
a caliber 9, judge, sir.
After beating him up. - Maybe it was
a settling of scores between pimps.
Judge, sir!
- Yes?
Look here.
There're all 100 Lire coins around.
Have they fallen or been placed?
During a fight?
I think they don't mean much.
Judge, sir, sign this paper.
There're traces of tires,
if that counts...
Get tire imprints!
Many whores are here every night.
Perhaps there're some witnesses.
That was my thought, too,
but whores won't talk.
First, try to identify the
victim. Keep me informed.
Certainly, judge, sir.
- Let's go.
If we exclude the name and the
job of the victim for a while,...
...I'd like to draw your
attention to three elements.
The place of the murder,
the signs of the fight...
...and the money that day Gagliardi
withdrew at his newspaper office.
An amount of money we couldn't
find any trace of,...
...after an investigation
lasting 48 hours.
Why trying to hide the most
serious aspect of this case?
It's front-page news, commissioner,
got it?
A journalist killed by mafia:
that's the first problem.
Mr Dalò, mafia has nothing
to do with this.
I could even concur with this
opinion,...
...but what counts now is what
one can read in the newspapers.
Dalò's right, and moreover we
can't absolutely underestimate...
...the deep impact of a murder
like this on the public opinion.
I've already received three
cables from Rome.
And I predict that a ministerial
inspector will arrive soon.
That is a public reputation of
inefficiency for the police, anyway.
Isn't like that? - When investigation
stops at the first findings,...
...a place frequented by whores,
a big amount of money disappeared...
Yet the hypothesis of robbery is
consequently the only plausible.
Justice doesn't want hypothesis but
certainty. - And some guilty parties.
We're talking about a murder for a
robbery and there're no suspects.
And neither evidence. - The prosecutor
has pinpointed the problem.
But all the elements acquired
so far head in this direction.
That's true, Mr Resta, but
until we reach a final result,...
...we shall allow room for
all the insinuations!
The victim's character actually
makes the public opinion skeptical.
Was it a robbery?
Give us the robber!
Anyway, we must refute the suspicion
that investigation isn't adequate.
Do you agree, chief, sir?
In general terms, yes.
I don't think we could do
more in two days.
We must do more, quickly, with no
prejudice, by all available means!
I always answered to no one!
Ask the chief.
I must admit that Mr Resta,...
...even if he moved to criminal
police a few weeks ago,...
...has all my confidence.
Gentlemen, let me say that
also experience counts,...
...especially as it's so hard to
avoid the influence of environment.
I said before that we must
go on firmly in this case.
At this point I ask the chief
for being relieved of this duty.
I've already had the opportunity
to appreciate your qualities.
Anyway, it's up to the chief
to make this decision.
Without humiliating any member
of the flying squad,...
...I think we have already a
character suited to this case.
- I'm led to believe you're thinking
of Miceli, aren't you? - Why not?
You forget his nature and the big
troubles he made for us in the past.
In a case like this you never
get away from criticism,...
...both having a too light or
a too heavy hand.
Criticism is welcome, but there
must be the results, at least.
Right, and Miceli happened to
be relieved of his duty...
...just for the way he used
to treat the prisoners.
That's a point made to many
policemen. - Never to me!
Chief, this problem falls within
your exclusive competence.
To think that I've to start to
fight with Miceli again isn't funny.
But I'll consider this solution too.
Hey, Luca!
There's a call for you via radio.
The chief wants to see you
right now.
I'm off duty, he just said to me:
"Get some rest, go to the beach,
stay out of my sight for a while".
Couldn't he have changed his mind?
- Yes, but he must change mine too.
Let him wait, let's have a coffee.
- Okay...
Is the chief upstairs?
- Yes. - Tell him I'm here.
He's calling in Rome now.
- Let him know I'm here.
Hey, Miceli, then don't say I'm
opposed to you: I did call you!
You? So it means you got troubles.
But fix them by yourself this time.
What's that supposed to mean? - I say:
"The right man in the right place".
You got there and now hang on it.
We understand each other.
Until you were here, you never
left anyone to breathe awhile.
Leave him to breathe. It's the safest
way to make your career. And you will.
Fuck off, Miceli!
- Anything to oblige.
Commissioner, he's already informed.
Go upstairs, he awaits you. - Thanks.
Sure, inspector.
Dear Miceli, your holidays
are over too.
I called to commit an assignment
of trust...
...and of a major responsibility
to you.
I esteem you, but I admit I've
put a lot of thought into this,...
...as someone else in my place
would have said:
"Better anyone than a troublemaker".
You actually got us in many troubles,
even in bad ones. Isn't like that?
Yes, I must have slapped some
faces...
...but who doesn't? My only mistake
was not to choose the right face.
Miceli, don't start again...
You're trying to say just to me...
That you can even push an asshole
around and take the job promotion!
But if you put your hands on one of
those who make the dirtiest tricks...
Listen to me! I've called you
because I esteem your qualities,...
...but you must not break
my balls now!
Excuse me, I care for you, but
it's not the time to argue.
The journalist killed two days ago
can turn into a kind of bomb,...
...and anyone who touches it
will be in very deep troubles.
So, do you want that bomb to be in my
hands, with all the other inspectors?
To think of the career you could have
made if you had been less arrogant...
You're still in time, Miceli.
I say to you, man to man:
"Find out this killer for me,...
...and I'll be very grateful".
I think Gagliardi had debt.
He looked worried, and just
that evening...
...he asked a down payment
on his expense account.
A million Lire, as I've already
told Mr Resta.
Your newspaper is so generous.
- He was a friend of mine,...
...as well as a collaborator,
and if a friend is in distress...
Did he tell you what that
money was for?
Once he mentioned some
mortgaged jewels, a pledge...
...which was about to expire, but
I didn't go any deeper into it.
What's up? - Excuse me, is the
draft of the front page ready?
No, just a moment, wait.
Which articles was Gagliardi
writing?
I don't know, I gave him
much freedom.
Really?
- I had every faith in him.
I just don't get it: a journalist
of yours is given a down payment,...
...then killed and you don't
even know what he was writing?
Enrico liked good life and women...
Given that he was a bit unscrupulous
as a journalist,...
...someone thinks that mafia
has to do with this.
But a year ago he wrote many
articles about this matter...
...and both me and him never
got into trouble.
Yes, I read them.
Well written.
Just that kind of reports which
don't add anything new,...
...just things everyone knows by
now and no longer bother anyone.
But one can even buy big news
and papers with a million Lire.
Or pay debt, get jewels unforeclosed...
At the pawnbroker's, right?
- I don't know, he didn't tell me.
But, remember, his corpse was found
in a place frequented by hookers.
Yes, I got it...he went to whores!
Let's wait for the end of
the season.
Have you found anything?
- No, and you? - Absolutely nothing.
Back to our office? - No, I can't
now and have something else to do.
Won't you write a report for
the chief?
Listen, I've got my problems too
and never a moment for them.
You don't know where I'm, if he
wants me. Got it? - Luca, but...
Hello, Luca.
- Hi.
I was starting to think you
wouldn't have come anymore.
I thought I was free, instead I'll
have a very urgent committment.
As usual.
- Daddy! - Hello!
Hi. Are we going to have breakfast
on the beach, as you told?
No, but wait for a while and
we'll go and get an icecream.
All right.
She was so proud to go and
have breakfast with you...
Weren't you given a rest period?
Is it an important thing?
- Well, yes, a bad one.
And...what about her?
Does she miss me a lot?
Yes, but she doesn't talk
about that.
How are you? Have you got the
wedding ring again?
You know, I don't want people to
call me "spinster" in front of Laura.
I think I'll keep on wearing it
for her, even after our divorce.
We should be summoned to the
courthouse soon.
When? - I don't know, but as soon as
a court date is set, I'll call you.
And what about our friends?
Do you meet them sometimes?
No. I don't like to hear people
feeling sorry for me.
I've to go. I'll take Laura for an
icecream and then drive her home.
Luca...
Put this on her, she must be sweaty.
She recovered just a week ago.
Sure. Bye.
Who is it?
- Commissioner Miceli?
Who is this?
- A friend. Listen to me.
If you want the journalist's killer,
check seafarers on board at the docks.
On which boat?
At the dock no. 4 there's
a fishing boat called "Plinio".
The wanted man is on board
and is going to clear off.
And...how do you know that?
Take my advice. You'll find also
a long barelled Luger caliber 9.
How many people are on board?
Who are you? What's your name?
- What do you want?
Police, let's see your I.D.
All right.
May I know why?
Shut up.
Luca, come down here!
What's up?
Get out of here!
Move!
Quick, c'mon!
Luca!
Don't tell you've even found a
long barelled Luger caliber 9.
Well?
Have I guessed right?
No! - So what?! Haven't you had
enough? Must I start again?
It's time to spit everything out!
My name's...Turi Delogo.
That badge isn't mine.
I found it on the ground.
And who put your picture on it?
Delogo, you were already prosecuted
twice for brawling and injuring,...
...and three times for robbery
and criminal conspiracy!
We know everything about you!
- You're even filed under "mafioso"!
No, they sentenced me to 18 months
imprinsonment for threats only once.
But it was due to a miscarriage
of justice, I swear.
Everything else's just calumniation.
The other times you got away
with it for lack of evidence!
But you won't this time!
The evidence's here!
Pay heed to me, you'd better
speak up!
I'm thirsty, commissioner.
- If you don't talk, you won't drink.
What do I have to say?
I know nothing about this!
Yes?
Sure.
Caliber 9, serial number: 87045.
What? In Delogo's name?
Are you sure? Fine. Thanks.
Now you'll stop telling lies,
scumbag!
That gun is yours, registered
in your name!
That's why he was going to
clear off with fake documents.
If that's the gun which killed
Gagliardi,...
...this time nobody will save
you from 30 years in prison.
Now cut the act, son of a bitch!
Speak!
Let me...All right, you made
me do this.
No...
- Let's start again!
It wasn't my fault! I swear,
I didn't mean to kill him.
It was...self-defense.
Delogo, what do you mean? Did you
actually shoot that journalist?
Yes. I...I didn't even know
who he was.
I was with a woman behind a bush,...
...and at some point I saw him
spying on us.
So I said to him: "Go away!".
He jump on me shouting insults
and threats.
To me...and to the woman who
was with me.
He spit in her face...and so
I shot that son of a bitch.
Send this to the forensic
department, immediately.
Tell them I won't do anything
until I get their report.
And send Terlizzi to me.
- All right.
Delogo, you don't fool me.
Now repeat everything word
for word.
Write down.
Enough.
Any time you change a thing of what
you said, we shall start again.
Got it?
- Yes.
Congratulations to you,
commissioner Miceli.
Don't you think...that's a bit
too early?
In little more than 24 hours,
we have got killer's name,...
...motive and notable evidence.
Press will pay tribute to this
efficiency.
I'd wait for the ballistics
report first.
Yes, of course, but we already
know the gun belonged to Delogo.
And Delogo has confessed.
We can consider the case solved.
Well...his confession isn't
convincing.
Why, commissioner?
Gagliardi killed because he
was spying on the couples?
And then, you didn't even
question him.
But I'll do in prison, and
if you ask me,...
...I can already tell you Delogo's
hiding the real motive: a robbery.
Delogo's a convicted felon,
judge, sir, he's an old fox.
Who's trying to avoid a charge
of murder with intent to rob!
And so he makes up the story
about the woman and the insults,...
...to claim self-defense and
extenuating circumstances!
And such an old fox allows himself
to be caught with a gun?
The weapon of the murder
registered in his name!
Now you're the naive one,
excuse me.
He felt sure more than ever on a
boat which was about to set sail.
Hello?
Yes, the commissioner Miceli's
already here, in my office.
Fine, Mr prosecutor, we shall
be with you in a minute.
I'm personally pleased that your
investigation was so quick. Indeed.
You know we never thought...
...much of commissioner Resta
here in this office.
But maybe you don't know that we
actually suggested to choose you.
Come, the prosecutor is waiting
for us.
Let's go and take our little
part of glory.
Tonight we're all sleeping a bit
more peacefully. Please, after you.
Have you transferred Delogo?
- No, there's a problem.
You, get out!
I called a van to take him to
prison, but in this condition...
Well, what's happened to you?
I fell off the folding bed
while sleeping.
I think I was dreaming.
- It's a nasty wound.
A self made one against the wall of
the cell, just before being transferred.
He can't be moved in such condition.
I confessed, you've to send me
to prison and can't hold me here!
So you go to infirmary and tell you
were beaten at the police station!
You don't fool me, Delogo!
I'll hold you here!
Given that he easily falls off
the folding bed, tie him to it.
He will be our guest until his
booboo ceases.
Take him away.
That guy can get us in trouble.
Watch him.
What did I tell you, Francesco?
He's already about to retract
his confession.
He will say you've extorted it from
him. - Right, it's his strategy.
By the way, what about the
ballistics report?
It's not ready, it will take
a few more days.
Fresh fish!
Nice fresh fish!
Caught at sea!
Pay me 600 Lire, I'll give it
away to you.
Fresh fish!
Caught at sea!
I was waiting just for you.
I've a special bite.
Look at this cod!
This is alive!
It's a bit pricey, but I've set it
aside for you. Will I clean it up?
Agreed, but your prices are
getting a bit too high.
Do you know the saying:
"Who goes fishing too close to a
dock, catches disgusting fish"?
I didn't catch to eat it, that's
why I'm trading with you.
You must look out for bones
when eating cod.
Sometimes they are so long
that they pierce your throat.
Any news? - Throw your net off
the coast for big fishes.
We give top notch fish only to
those who pay well. - Yes, I know.
Thanks.
- C'mon, speak up.
The dead sea bream was after
a red mullet: Rosaria.
They were seen together.
- What's her surname?
I don't know. Let me go,
somebody's watching us.
Where can I find her?
- I don't sell puncturing fish.
Ask "Yo-yo", she was one of his
loyal customers.
Your name and surname.
- Caciotti Giuseppina.
What's your job?
- Housewife.
I'm sleepless, I've to walk
by night, so I get tired then.
Sure, you must get tired
walking all night long.
I've wasted two hours.
Who will pay me back?
Excuse me, why a lady like me
has to stay with such people?
This friend of mine is going
to marry a count!
You'll regret this!
- You'll pay for this!
Keep calm!
Keep quiet!
Come!
Good evening, commissioner.
I'm here but it's like I weren't.
I inform you I won't speak, if
first my lawyer doesn't come.
Am I right?
I know nothing, anyway.
Well said...You said you won't
speak, right?
No! Do not touch me!
Do not touch me, got it?
Recchia Aminta, nicknamed "Yo-yo".
Drugs pusher and pimp!
I know you too. If you touch me,
I'll report you to the prosecutor.
Who says I'll touch you, "Yo-yo"?
I'll tell a name and you'll tell
a surname, not to waste your time.
You're actually wasting your time,
commissioner.
Her name's Rosaria.
A loyal customer of yours, a high-priced
whore. I want her surname and address.
Who does know her?!
I don't have to do with such women.
Last time you were here,
it costed you one tooth!
Careful, this time I'll knock
all your teeth out!
Be careful not to be fired.
I've got important friends.
All right, "Yo-yo", let's do
as you like.
C'mon, get undressed.
I said: "Get undressed".
Get undressed!
You've got a nice shirt,
it'd be a pity to stain it.
Don't be afraid, this won't
leave marks.
Let's make a nice little job,
a high class one.
Rosaria...Cruciani?
You're a good boy, "Yo-yo".
Well said.
Are you sure she came back?
- Yes.
Was her alone? - Yes. Maybe she
got a sleeping pill and can't hear.
Open.
You stay there.
Francesco!
Smell it.
It smells like cyanide.
Yes, it seems to me too.
A heroin dose mixed with cyanide.
A good way to get rid of an addict.
Will I inform the police station?
- No!
Let's take a look, first.
You look here, I'll go downstairs.
Luca!
What's up? - Look what I've found.
There's an engraving on it.
"With love, from Enrico to Fiorenza."
Yes, I remember. When he bought
it, he showed me.
He wanted to give it to a woman
he was engaged with.
They had to marry, then broke up.
An old story fizzled out.
He was like that.
Thanks. - Just out of curiosity:
where did you find it?
Certainly not at the pawnbroker's.
I can't tell you more.
See that some jewels were involved?
I first talked to you about it.
True, but how many more important
things could you tell about him?
The truth is that when one dies that
way, nobody'd like to have known him.
I already told all that I knew.
- Right.
Is Delogo the killer, isn't he?
Commissioner, why don't you go
to the administrative office?
Ask them for viewing Gagliardi's
expense lists. It's worth.
Here're all the reimbursement
lists made for him lately.
He drank whiskey for 300,000 Lire
at Continental's bar last month.
It says that.
You treat your journalists well, sending
them to night clubs at your expense.
No way. As you can see, there's the
editor's approval on the lists.
That means he used to go there
for work.
And didn't he have to account
for his expense in each case?
Supposedly he had to.
What qualified him to withdraw a
million Lire the day he was killed?
Gagliardi had special assignments.
In this case, you'd know which
kind of articles he was writing.
Did...you ask the editor?
- He says he doesn't know.
If he doesn't, how can I know?
Hotel Continental...
Do you still need my help?
- No, thanks. - You're welcome.
If they wanted to kill me, they
would have set a bigger bomb.
Just a little warning, nothing else.
I'm stepping on someone's feet.
Delogo's better. Send him to jail
and let the judge deal with him.
So he will question and charge him and
the case will be closed. - Suck it up.
Do you think I really like playing
the hero? The crappy hero...
But I don't want to play the role
of the dumb like in the past!
And then I'm sure Gagliardi
had discovered something.
What if it was actually a robbery?
That ring was in a whore's house.
She died too.
Well, look what a coincidence.
Sorry, I never lend money
by or without pledge.
They told me that here, a ring
like this...
At the bar? No. Have your tried
to ask Rosenthal?
Does he lend money by pledge? - He's
an expert and is there, in the hall.
Will you buy me a drink?
Give me another one.
Are...you completely alone?
Right.
But I've a lot to do now.
Rosenthal? Is it you?
- Yes.
Look at this.
Are you interested?
Well, I could give you 100,000
Lire.
So little? You offered more in
the past. - I don't think so.
But...do you remember you've
already seen it?
Judging by the shape, I'd say yes,
but God knows where and when.
Did you bring it to me?
- No, but you'd remember.
A lot of people come here,
if I had to remember any face...
No. And then, it's the kind of
stuff I'm not interested in.
Who are you? Can you tell me
where you bought that ring?
I no longer remember.
Why don't you invite me to dinner?
I've had a pretty tough day.
I'm going to bed.
I'm going home, can you give
me a ride, at least?
I don't have a car, it's broken.
- But I do have it!
Look, you're wasting your time,
I haven't got any change.
I've only asked you for going with
me and if you feel tired... - What?
I'll get you a cup of coffee.
I told you: who drinks my coffee
once, then comes here again.
Wouldn't I? - How stupid, you
knew I was waiting for you.
It's rather nice here.
- Do you like it?
There must be a nice business
at the Continental.
Oh, no, the fact is that I've
got some good friends.
And if you have no friends,
you can't do much today.
Right.
My job is the unluckiest one.
I make nothing but enemies.
And I risk my neck every day
for starvation wages.
But you've got a new car now.
Do you think the government
bought me a new car?
I know.
- It gave me a big scare.
Guess what happened to me yesterday
morning, just after I left you.
It's a gift by some good friend.
Which friend? My friends aren't
rich. - My friends are.
Do they mind that I sleep with
you? I thought they were angry.
What do you know? Instead they're eager
to know you and can do much for you.
See that I bring you luck?
Aren't you pleased with me?
What does the judge want from us?
Why does he summon us?
You know, it's a legal step.
He will say: "Give it a second thought,
as a marriage's a serious thing".
One who doesn't know us at all
will make us change our minds?
We had many years to think hard,
before getting to this point.
They do that...not to deprive
sons of their family warmth.
Have we ever been a family?
It's this crummy job which makes
you lose confidence in yourself,,...
...in the people, in everything,
giving you nothing back in return!
I still can't get what you want
from life. - I don't even know!
I only know that one must jump
in deep shit to get something!
Didn't me and Laura do any
good to you?
What do you have to do with this?
I didn't even do any good to you.
Do you know Laura asked me to
send her to a boarding school?
What comes to her mind?
She says that maybe she won't
feel so alone there.
Hello.
- Let's go this way.
You know, it's not easy to be
admitted to this club.
It takes time before being invited.
That means you're important.
Place your bets.
What's going on over there?
- Nothing. People playing cards.
End of bets, nothing goes on
the table.
Fourteen, red, even, failed.
Do you know I could be charged
with misconduct in public office?
Why? - Gambling is a crime, I'd
have to arrest all the people.
But it's a high class club, even
politicians use to come here.
Right, and policemen. - So what?
How much money do you have?
40,000 Lire. - I'm in the mood
for game, let's play Chemin de fer.
Come.
- But...are you crazy?
I'm actually a lucky woman.
You won't regret.
Bank at 20,000.
Bank player.
Card.
Bank wins the hand.
Bank at 40,000.
Any offer? Bank passes.
40,000, next play.
40,000? Any play?
Anyone?
Ask the bank.
- Bank to player.
Bank.
- Bank at 40,000.
Bank changes at 40,000.
- Bank to next player.
Bank wins, bank at 80,000.
"Banco suivi".
Card.
Three for the play.
Bank wins. Bank at 160,000.
Eight.
Nine, bank wins.
Bank at 320,000.
Who plays for 320,000?
Zero. Bank wins again.
Bank at 640,000.
It's time to stop.
If you want, you can come back
a couple of times per month,...
...to make up your wages.
And what if I lose instead?
- You can't lose.
What am I being asked in exchange?
- Nothing.
What matters is that my friends
are satisfied with you.
Pleased? Excuse me, they don't
even know me, I never met them.
There was no need.
They actually saw you.
Excuse me, help me to understand,
you wrote here:...
..."From the analysis of the rifling
of the barrel one's led to assume..."
"...that the examined weapon
is the same the killer used."
"Comparing the barrel with the bullet
which caused Gagliardi's death..."
"...the visible riflings
are almost identical."
"Almost identical"...
What the heck does this mean?
In short, are they identical
or not?
It means that one can find more
riflings into the barrel.
One could say that they were
added after the gun shot.
One can spot the same on the
shells. Look here.
The first shell was found next
to Gagliardi's corpse. See?
This is the shell of a shot
fired by me...
...with the gun you sent me.
The notch of the hammer is the
same on both the shells.
But it's deeper and more irregular
on the second one. See?
How do we know the hammer
hasn't been altered later?
Got it. In other words,
at the Court of Assizes,...
...the defense will be able to
claim there's no definite proof...
...about the gun which killed
Gagliardi.
In my opinion, I firmly believe
that's the gun which killed him.
But it must have been altered
later.
But we can't prove that.
That means we've got a proof
which proves nothing.
Who knows. Thanks, anyway. - You know
my theory about technical reports.
They prove the truth, but if one
wanted to, even the opposite.
See you.
- Take care. - Bye.
Terlizzi, you'll do that later,
go and have a coffee.
Thanks.
What do you think about that?
It's clear, isn't it?
He will be acquitted for lack of evidence,
with such report and no witnesses.
Now we can understand the fake
anonymous call, the fishing boat,...
...the gun inside the berth,
the fake I.D...
Everything's been prefabricated.
- Get Delogo in here.
If he doesn't eat all his words,
I'll beat him to death!
Do not touch him, Luca,
all the eyes are on you.
He must retract all the lies
he told us!
Retract? - Yes, all of them. Better
here than at the Court of Assizes.
Tell him that, as soon as he retracts,
I'll release him immediately.
If he pretended to be guilty, it means
he figures he's got his bases covered.
That's why he's more useful
out of prison!
When he's free, his protectors
will start to worry again.
Someone will be afraid. It's the only
way to open the investigation again.
Rosaria Cruciani was a call girl at
Continental and Gagliardi knew her.
But it's pointless to ask.
Nobody knows anything or saw them.
And as soon as we follow that lead,
we can say goodbye to Rosaria.
They're talking about suicide. - Right.
- Beware, Luca, you're aiming too high.
I know.
I have to!
I can prove that someone's
aiming higher than me!
Let's release Delogo.
- Okay.
Warm greetings
Rosaria
Why are you interested in Djerba? What
have you found? We're interested too.
A mere postcard, posted by a
woman who was killed later,...
...a certain Rosaria Cruciani.
She was an addict. I've to know
why she went to Djerba.
If you tell me whom she went with,
I'll answer you.
If I knew, I wouldn't have
called the Interpol.
You make fun of us, but then
ask for our help, don't you?
Djerba has long been the favourite
meeting point for drug smugglers.
During the period you're
interested in, there was even...
...a summit meeting of the
international godfathers.
Also Italian guys? - One for sure.
He really kept us very busy.
Let's sit down, they prepare
some very good cakes here.
My stomach is all messed up since
I cook by myself or go to self-service...
Are you still separated from
your wife?
You know, by now...until I decide
to change my job...
It's hard to come back.
But back to us. Tell me everything
about that Italian guy at Djerba.
You'd have to check which was
the woman with him.
It's a question I can't answer.
We have been after that man
for more than two years.
We think he controls the drug
which moves from East to Sicily.
I just can tell you a name:
Mauro D'Amico.
Don't you have a profile
I can take a look at?
When they sent me here,
I found nothing but his name.
There must have been a dossier
about him.
Any paper about him disappeared
from the archive. No pictures.
What's left is only a reporting
of two years ago, at Hamburg.
He run away after a firefight with
the police, but he was wounded,...
...maybe at his leg.
What has the drug to do with
your case? - I don't know.
What have you found?
- A postcard. Nothing else.
Watch Delogo, ok?
When did he get out?
A hour ago.
We keep an eye on him.
I can imagine the chief's face,
when he comes to know.
We shall have a lot of laugh...
He will raise such a ruckus.
Send him your report, pay heed to me.
At least, you'll explain your reasons.
If you want wine, get yourself
a glass. - No, thanks.
Listen to me.
Now have this address stuck in
your head: Alcamo avenue, 42.
It's a private club, where
people gamble by night.
There must be almost 30 other
clubs in the city, you know.
And nobody touches them.
But we shall take a look at this.
And for what?
- That club is almost a brothel.
Gambling is just a pseudo-activity,
but they actually deal drugs behind.
Inform DEA.
Sure! Say just a word to them
and you'll fuck up our surprise!
No, it's just a job you have
to do for me. Tonight.
Choose a dozen men and turn up
at here around midnight.
And arrest whoever you find.
Feel free to sweep there. Agreed?
Luca, look, we shall stir up
a hornets' nest.
Do you want to back down?
- No, but may I speak as a friend?
We're friends, aren't we?
- I must ask you a question.
I already know it, Francesco.
You want to know why I always
do things the hard way,...
...why I enjoy to drive everybody
away all the times.
I couldn't even hold together
my family.
And you're fed up with this too.
Is that what you wanted to ask me?
Let's forget it. Have you said
"Alcamo avenue", haven't you?
I'll be there at midnight, but
it's the last time. Bye. - Bye.
Simona, it's me, Luca.
Are you free tonight?
Listen, I need to see you.
Do your friends really care
about that club?
What do you mean? - I heard they
will get some troubles tonight.
There will be a surprise around
midnight.
Are you mad?!
- No kidding, look out.
One of their important friends
must have informed them.
Listen, I couldn't do more than inform
you. It's a serious thing, you know?
Excuse me for a moment.
Four men stay here, the others
follow me!
Nobody move! Everybody stay
in your seats.
Lock the doors!
Nobody move! Everybody stay in your
seats. Do not touch fiches and money!
It's pointless, you can't get
out anyway!
I've to point out that my office
didn't order that operation.
Have a seat.
Sit down, Mortesi.
I was sure about it, but I protest
about your commissioner's conduct!
It's a real affront to the
judicial authority!
I completely agree with the
prosecutor's point of view.
Both me and you know Miceli...
...and you insisted to entrust
Gagliardi's case to him.
Agreed!
But how could a prosecutor
expect such absurd initiatives?!
First, Delogo's affair, then this
order for a search with no warrant!
We all made mistakes.
Without exception.
And we all shall have to
pay a little.
Mortesi, let me understand: have
you got a written order? - No.
But, I say, he must have given
you some instructions,...
...or have said: "Go to that
gambling house, seize everything,..."
"...and arrest all of them
like criminals"!
The more big cheeses you find
there, the less care about them.
They always make the real bullshits.
Because it's the way he gives orders.
I want to know what this operation
has to do with Gagliardi's case!
He only told me there had to be
a drug trafficking in that club.
Drug? What did you find?
- Drug was not found.
Drug or not, anyway, gambling
is a crime punished by law!
Let's not confuse things! I don't
want to discuss a police operation.
But, since the authorisation from
a judicial authority is missing,...
...the order for a search given by
commissioner Miceli is unlawful!
Why didn't he ask me for a warrant?
You well know that timeliness,
resolution and absolute secrecy...
...are needed for these operations.
Oh! Very well!
So Miceli thought secrecy would have
been compromised talking to me.
At this point, there's nothing
more that can be said.
Miceli acted tactlessly and
too hastily. It's his nature.
No! Miceli committed some real
abuses and on purpose!
What do you think to do, judge,
sir?
In my opinion, any measure we
may adopt in such a moment,...
...we run the risk to get
exposure for a matter...
...which has already put both you
and us in a negative situation.
The surprise at the club can have
very serious consequences, prosecutor.
Don't forget that some club
members are actually big names.
To each his own responsibility,
I can't say more,...
...but I'm here for another
serious reason as well.
I mean Delogo's affair.
Abusive release, failure to fulfil
obligations about investigation...
You can only recognize Miceli's
conduct is exceeding all limits.
Only the great consideration
towards you...
...has stopped us from taking
initiatives...
...which we prefer you take by
your responsibility and authority.
Listen, Mortesi, go and find
Miceli for me immediately.
I went to his house, called him
three times, where the hell is he?
He must come here. I predicted
we would get to this point.
If he's got out on duty, call him via
radio. I want him here right away.
Sorry, I've to leave you, the club's
president is waiting over there...
That's a problem I've to solve
by myself.
Frankly, I wouldn't like to
be in your place these days.
For the rest, after your assurance,
we can consider this incident closed.
See you, prosecutor, sir.
- Good evening.
Mom, it's me. We go to the
restaurant with Letizia.
Have you put the kids to bed?
- Don't be late.
Hello, who's there?
- It's me, Simona. Is he here?
Yes.
- Put him through, it's urgent.
What's up? - Bad news,
inform your friends right away.
The tourists are coming
to the club tonight.
What?
- Yes, the tourists.
Are you mad?!
- Don't waste your time.
I've come to know that
right now, inform the others.
Who did tell you?
- You know who's: Luca.
Are you sure? Can he avoid this?
- No, he can't.
To which number is being made
this call?
To 97381, Gambino, import and
export.
Storage and headquarters:
Buongiovanni street, 30.
What a pity I missed that scene.
The old man was really angry.
- He will await, what can I do?
I've an ace up my sleeve. Why to
ruin it dropping down on his knees?
Where are we going? I don't actually
want to ruin my own career.
If you stop, you'll ruin it!
May I help you?
- Come with me, Mauro D'Amico.
There must be a mistake,
I'm Gunther Rosenthal.
Agreed, Mr Rosenthal, come and
we shall check your identity.
In the meanwhile, you're under
arrest for loansharking. Help him.
Stop that, do not touch me,
I need no help.
But, just be careful what you do,
commissioner. - Let's go, c'mon.
What are you looking for?
- I'm going to the prosecution office.
Aren't you aware nobody's here
on Saturday? The office's closed.
The prosecutor and his assistant
come back home on Friday night.
Someone must be covering a shift,
at least. Who's? Where's he?
You'd better come back on Monday.
- Wait, idiot!
I'm Miceli, the police commissioner...
...and I've to know who's the
assistant and where is!
Mr Dalò is on duty but is
on his boat now.
I want to know where I can find him!
- At the port authority.
They use to call him via radio for
urgent things. I can't tell you more.
Nice flag...Panama...
Sorry, commissioner, do you
still need my help?
No, thanks, go ahead.
- Thanks.
Good evening, commissioner.
- Good evening, sir.
What's so urgent that you've
called me?
As you can see, I've some guests.
I'm sorry, but it's extremely
important.
Have you got a scoop to offer?
What else have you discovered?
The real motive why Gagliardi
was murdered.
Excuse me for a moment.
- Yes, but hurry up. - Come.
And which is the real motive,
in your opinion?
Gagliardi was preparing a
report about mafia,...
...rather, he discovered the real
identity of a mafioso convicted felon.
He goes by Rosenthal. Interpol was
after him for drug trafficking.
But do you have the evidence
of what you're saying?
His real name's Mauro D'Amico,
he used to hide at Continental.
Gagliardi unmasked him and he
got rid of him.
He's even a loan shark.
I've arrested him.
By which kind of indictment?
I told you, he manages an
international drug trafficking.
But do you have the evidence
of what you're saying?!
You only need to identify him.
- Miceli...!
But that's what is called
abuse of power!
We live in a civil country!
We're in a democracy!
Your conduct is in sharp contrast
to the rules of our penal code!
I've been looking for you since this
morning to get the arrest warrant signed!
A prosecutor doesn't put out arrest
warrants until facts are examined!
I know, but while facts are
examined,...
...the suspect in a serious crime
has all the time to run off!
Miceli, you've been incredibly
lucky.
You've been entrusted with an
investigation,...
...you happened to get the killer, his
confession and evidence in your hands!
Yes, it's true, they have put
what they wanted in my hands,...
...just to manoeuvre me like
a puppet!
Let's try to keep calm.
Delogo was nothing but a red
herring for the public opinion!
But you have understood just
nothing.
Delogo actually killed Gagliardi!
- What about the instigators?
When this case goes to trail
in a couple of years,...
...Delogo will be certainly
acquitted for lack of evidence!
Here's the manoeuvre! - Delogo killed
and you didn't have to release him!
In exchange, you're bringing a
loan shark arrested unlawfully!
I told you that Delogo's a
false target...
...and I'm not so stupid that
someone can jerk me!
I ask you to watch your language!
All right, I'm watching my language,
but I won't play the role of the puppet!
Wait!
Well, my office will check the
elements you brought and decide.
But...never here.
And very calmly.
Nicola, what's up?
- Excuse me.
I need a line.
And I risk my neck every day
for starvation wages.
But you've got a new car now.
Do you think the government
bought me a new car?
It's a gift by some good friend.
My friends aren't rich.
My friends are and can do
much for you.
Love, how much have you
won tonight?
640,000 Lire! Just in half a hour!
Forget the Christmas bonus!
What did I tell you?
Listen, I've called my friends.
They are very pleased with you.
There're two other tapes.
And do you...believe in that?
No, my friend, I don't, but
all the others...
You know the truth, I've always
informed you about everything.
But if a commission of inquiry
listens to those tapes,...
...a saint won't be able to
protect you, either.
But I didn't touch even a coin
of that amount of money!
And that was the only way to
find out the instigators!
How old are you, Miceli?
After being here all these years
long, you still didn't learn...
Learn what?!
I know you, you're a honest
person, but, watch out,...
...by dint of butting, even a bull
ends up with cracking its horns...
...and gets stuck.
Well, I think every man has his
own season, just like the plants.
Miceli, you're out of season.
Do you remember when I told you:
"Get some rest, go to the beach"?
Who could stab me in the back?
Who gave you those tapes?
Don't worry, this thing will
be completely confidential.
A scandal would be useful to
nobody,...
...not even to the prosecutor's
men.
Are we fooling around? A police
commissioner being investigated!
Now you'll take a nice leave
for health or family reasons...
I didn't asked you for a leave,
I don't want a leave!
And let's make it quite clear:
I'm not afraid of a scandal at all!
I'm, instead.
- Well, let me ask you a question!
Are you ready to sign an arrest
warrant for Mauro D'Amico?
Miceli, let's try to be reasonable,...
...isn't enough the mess you made
just to do it all your way?
No, excuse me, I've asked you
a question!
What will you decide to do
about Mauro D'Amico?
Gunther Rosenthal, whom you insist
to call Mauro D'Amico,...
...was released two hours ago.
You well know that law asks that
a loan shark is caught in the act.
Unfortunately, your arrest was
illegal.
I got it all.
And since things are like that,
I'll leave.
I thought we served justice
and truth.
Because we are all seeking
truth here,...
...but ready to turn a blind eye,
as soon as truth becomes thorny.
Do you think we can be back
one day?
They will forget everything,
as time goes by.
Simona, I...I'll be back.
Right now! What are you waiting for?!
- Beyond the curve!
Fire! Again!
And now?
Where do you think you can go?
I don't know.
I'll catch a plane and fly away.
Dad, come here. I've finished a
castle, help me to put the flag.
Well, why don't you put?
- There's no need.
If there's a flag, they can
see it's our castle.
The enemies will keep away.
This castle can't have enemies.
It's in a country where all
the people are just friends.
Bye, I've to go.
At 3:20 pm,
flight no. L27 via Rome,...
...with a connecting flight
to Nice, Paris, destination...
fansubbed by quidtum April 2015